I'm really looking forward to this one.
Today I'm going to make my first YouTube
video ice cream, which is lemon mering
pie. But I've learned a lot over the
years. Let's see how much better I can
make this one.
Yeah. So, like I said last week, the um
my top five ice creams, I'm going to
remake them. I'm going to also throw in
some other videos just in the buildup to
Christmas cuz, you know, why not? Um
lemon merang pie. It's It's one of my
favorite desserts, one of my wife's
favorite desserts. And that ice cream
that I made back then all those years
ago was freaking delicious. And I'm
looking forward to remaking it. I've
learned a lot over the years. You know,
I I make ice cream commercially. I
develop recipes for commercial
companies, startups, and and the like.
So, you know, I I dread to think of how
many ice cream recipes I've actually
made over the years. Into the thousands,
for sure. A couple of notes before we
get dug into this is the meringue part.
Like I said in last week's video, taking
store-bought pre-made meringues and
putting them in ice cream just doesn't
work. They just turn to mush. Uh you can
actually freeze dry meringues, made
merings, homemade merangs, and then you
can use them in ice cream. That's the
way to do it. Any remaining moisture
just allows the absorption of more
moisture into that from the ice cream
base, turns your meringue into mush.
We're not going to do that this time,
though. We're going to do a Swiss mering
swirl. We're going to do a lemon ice
cream base with delicious buttery graham
crumb cubes. So, with all that said,
what are we going to need for this
updated version of lemon mering pie ice
cream? 592
gram of whole milk. 582 g of cream at 33
to 36% fat. If you use UK double cream,
reduce that down to 500 gram, 230 gram
of sugar, 24 gram of invert sugar,
glucose or corn syrup, 65 g of skim milk
powder, and 6 g of lemon extract. All
the stats for this ice cream will be on
Patreon and will be available for
YouTube members as well. And that
includes the fat percentage, sugar, milk
solids, non-fat, water, and solids
content along with your pack and pod.
Let's get everything out and going.
Right. So, let's start off with our
milk, which is 592 g. Into that, we're
going to put our cream, 582 g. Our
sugar, 230 g. I'm going to put 220. And
keep 10 aside. And I'm going to use corn
syrup today. You can use glucose syrup.
You can use honey. It's not the same,
but it's close enough. Glucose syrup,
inverted sugar, corn syrup, 24 g.
Going to get a little container.
Last 10 g of sugar. Now, I'm going to
cook this base with a high temperature
stabilizer. So, this is locust bean gum
in here. That's all I'm going to use
today. Just going to swirl that together
with that last little bit of sugar. One
little lump there. Go away. you in. That
goes. Lastly, our milk powder, which is
65 g.
With all those ingredients in there,
let's just get that milk powder
mixed in. We got two sources of lemon
flavor. Lemon extract, lemon zest. This
lemon is number 4,53.
It's not I don't know what that number
means. Um, two slightly different flavor
profiles. This one, Nilson Macy, which
is available in sainsburries to those
people that moan that I don't tell you
where to get extracts from. Literally go
to the supermarket and just look for
them. There's hordes of these in
sainsburries and I even think Tesco sell
it. So, yes, it's an American brand.
It's one of the best. You can use one or
the other. You don't have to use both,
but I want to use both. My local
supermarket use wax lemons, but easy way
to tell, run your fingernail over the
top. If the wax comes off on your
finger, then you just need to wash it
under warm water. It's done to protect
them from going bad too early. So, we're
going to shave some of that
in our ice cream. You don't need a
massive amount. I'm only going to go for
half a lemon's worth cuz I'm also going
to add extract after the event. By
adding the lemon zest into our base, now
we're allowing that natural
lemon oil that's in this the zest to
come out during the heating phase. Adds
a really nice and I actually quite like
to leave that lemon zest in there. If
you don't want to, then you can strain
it, but you're missing out. Anyway,
let's get this on the hob and get this
heated up. This is locust bean coming
here, so I'm going up to 185. I'm going
to keep it there for, you know, 5
minutes and then I'll take it off and
we'll carry on. Right. While that is
heating up, I'm just going to keep an
eye on it periodically. In we go with
our honey graham crumbs. We're going to
use 200 g.
And we're going to need half the weight
in butter.
So, 100 g of butter.
That is fine. Butter.
I'm going to put this in the microwave
to melt it.
In that goes there.
Stir that together. I like my pie crust
pieces in ice cream to be really
buttery. It gives a better texture in
the ice cream so it doesn't go like rock
solid. Um you can add a little bit of
sugar to this if you want to. That is
absolutely fine. I'm not this time. But
there we go. Our butter is incorporated
into our graham crumb. Going to get a
little bit of foil in there. And that
goes into our pan.
It already smells nice. And we're just
going to flatten that down
like so.
And that is going to go into the oven at
300F for only 5 to 8 minutes. Not long.
All right. So, that goes in there. Now
I'm going to get back on the ice cream
base. We're off the heat. This is kind
of cooling down now a little bit.
I It doesn't take long. We're down to
60C now. It really only takes a couple
of minutes to go from 80 85 C down to
about 60c. Doesn't take long. We're in a
safer zone to use our extract. So super
strong smell. Love this stuff. In goes
a good 10 g. We want this lemony.
All right. But using the two different
sources of lemon flavor, it just brings
out a more natural balance. So it just
tastes like lemon should. I find lemon
ice cream is often way too weak or super
super tart and too strong. So getting
that balance, that's up to you. If you
just want to use the lemon, the lemon
zest, then use the zest from one whole
lemon and allow it to steep whilst
cooking it. If you want to do a cold
processed stabilizer, then use the milk
and infuse the lemon zest into the milk
first. Allow that to infuse for, you
know, at least an hour. Heat it up and
let it sit off the hob then for a good
hour. Um, and then you can start mixing
all your cold items back together.
That's everything done for our base. In
that goes.
Make sure that zest goes in there as
well. In the fridge it goes overnight.
We'll let those flavors develop. Let
that lemon oil come out of that zest as
well. So, we got a couple of minutes
left on our graham crumb. That will come
out the oven and then I will let that
cool down completely to room temperature
and cube it up and then pop that in the
refrigerator too. Tomorrow we'll make
the Swiss meringue. Nice easy way to
make it coming
in a minute. Right, it's the next day
and my new apron has turned up and I
don't like it because if you're old
enough to watch the original Juice of
Hazard, it makes me look like Uncle
Jesse.
Either way, that's what I got. So, the
the the oven's on for something else, so
excuse the noise if you can hear it. And
we've got our ice cream base. It's ready
to churn. We're going to get our
meringue, which this is a Swiss mering.
It's really easy to to make Swiss
mering. What we're going to do is we're
going to start with our egg yolks. I've
got some remaining carton egg yolks
here. That's absolutely fine. 100 g.
And then we're going to add some glucose
syrup. Again, corn syrup is glucose
syrup, but not all glucose syrup is corn
syrup. We're going to add 30 g. And into
that, I am going to add
1/4 teaspoon. So that's about 1 and a2
gram of cream of tartata. You can use
citric acid as well if you're not a fan
of this. I don't know why you wouldn't
be. It's just stuff. Now we're going to
put about an inch worth of water in this
pan. That's going to heat up. We're
going to whisk this together off the
heat
like that. And we're going to get this
sat over the top of our water. So this
is a banmarie.
So, we're going to get this sat over top
of that water and cook it out until it's
75 centrade, which is this in
Fahrenheit. Then, when it's at that
temperature, we're going to take it off
and put it back here and whisk it within
an inch of its life. All right, we're up
to 70 C, actually, not 75, because all
the egg whites have obviously melted
that sugar and it's become a nice
homogeneous fluffy mix. Now is the time
to get your ice cream machine machine
chilling down because
I am going to get my hand mixer.
And as you can see, it doesn't reach. So
I'm going to have to come back here and
do it. And I'm just going to whisk this
egg whites. Our Swiss mering is going to
take about 15 to 20 minutes to whisk up
and cool. And that will create that
really lovely delicious pillowy Swiss
mering that we're going to use. Very
much like marshmallow because the
addition of that glucose syrup. So,
whilst we're going to wait for that,
we're going to get our really nice I
mean, this is 14% fat, this ice cream.
So, this is going to be really, really
luxurious. So, we're going to get some
in here. Get this churning whilst we
carry on with our Swiss mering.
Right, we've got our meringue whipped
up. We're really just going down to room
temperature, which is where we're at
now. We're at 21 centrade now. So, that
is good to go. So, a smooth marshmallow
kind of texture. That's kind of what
you're aiming for. So, with everything
ready, the last thing to do to our Swiss
mering is to add some vanilla extract.
We're going to add
a good one to two teaspoons. Make it
taste of vanilla. And stir that in.
Now, we just need to wait for the ice
cream. Then, we can dish up. Load
everything in there. We got everything
ready, including our lovely buttery
graham cracker crumb, our Swiss mering,
and our lemon ice cream. Towards the end
of the churn, if your machine is strong
enough, then you can just drop your
graham cracker cubes in there like I'm
doing here. If it's not strong enough or
you're not sure, then just stir them in
by hand after you load up your tub.
These muso are really strong and can
cope with this. But when it comes to
dishing and serving up time, we're going
to put a good spoon of our ice cream in.
Then some of our delicious vanilla Swiss
meringue, followed by some more ice
cream. And we're going to keep going and
doing that until we fill up our tubs.
Because right at the end, we're going to
top off with a few cubes of our Graham
cracker crumb. And then get that in the
freezer.
Oh, it's uh early
due to child care. I'm having to eat ice
cream at 7:49 in the morning. So, it's
Thursday morning. It's still dark
outside. This is early even for me. But
you got to do what you got to do. Lemon
mering pie ice cream.
That natural lemon smell from that zest.
Oh, got it on my nose. That lemon
extract from Neielson Macy is perfect.
So, we've got a really delicious, easy
to scoop ice cream. Serving temperature
minus4. So, when you take it out of the
freezer, you can kind of just dig in.
You don't have to wait for it to soften
up, you know, blah blah blah. You can
see the super shiny meringue, Swiss
mering in there. That looks delicious.
And the graham cracker crumb. I'm going
in. Happy Thursday morning.
That is so delicious. That lemon ice
cream is perfect. A perfect amount of
flavor to that. The super buttery graham
cracker pieces. They don't go super hard
cuz there's such a high amount of butter
in there. So, it kind of just melts in
your mouth now and you're [snorts] left
with that glorious buttery aftertaste.
The meringue. So, Swiss meringue.
Super smooth. No separation.
Nice vanilla taste to it as well. I
mean, you know, I I just eat that stuff
on its own. So, so delicious. I'm really
glad I remade this one. It's been years
since I've made this. So, lemon mering
pie ice cream. If you want to burn that
that meringue a little bit, kind of add
a toastiness to it, that would be really
good. So if you want to do that, then I
recommend just torching it a little bit,
stirring it together. Torch it a little
bit, stir it together. Then you get
those little pieces of burnt meringue in
there. So adds a really nice smoky
flavor to it. So that's a really nice
thing to do. You could also just plon
some meringue on top, burn that off as
well. That would be delicious.
Ultimately,
incredible ice cream. Really, really
glad I remade this one. Next week, I'm
going to do a remake of Salted Straws,
salted molted chocolate chip cookie
dough. There's two different types of
cookie dough. Loads of malt flavor in
there. It's incredible. Or it was when I
first made it. Is it still as good?
Let's make it again and find out. Don't
forget to like and subscribe. Thanks
very much for watching and I'll see you
guys next week.
[music]